<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lively pourtraict of our new-cavaliers, commonly called Presbyterians clearly shewing that His Majesty came not in upon their account : in a compendious narrative of our late revolutions.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21337</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12406192</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12406192</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61392</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48756)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61392)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 767:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lively pourtraict of our new-cavaliers, commonly called Presbyterians clearly shewing that His Majesty came not in upon their account : in a compendious narrative of our late revolutions.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterians --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61392:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LIVELY POURTRAICT OF OUR New-Cavaliers, Commonly Called PRESBYTERIANS.</p>
            <p>CLEARLY SHEWING, That His MAIESTY came not in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Account.</p>
            <p>In a Compendious Narrative of our late Revolutions.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device with crown surmounting spread-winged bird</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61392:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61392:2"/>
            <head>A Lively POURTRAICT OF OUR NEW CAVALIERS, Commonly Called PRESBYTERIANS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT, in the leaſt, to blemiſh the loyalty of any, who (late, indeed, but ſeaſonably,) became Proſelytes, And, with ſubſequent Merits, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled the memory of their former Errours, Yet, for that many Perſons of unbyaſſed Principles, are apt to be miſled with this vulgar Prejudice, That the Presbyterians were the Principal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his Majeſties Reſtauration, From the jealouſie and diſdain, which, (as a paſſionate Lover of his Majeſty,) I conceive at the very mention of ſuch a Rival, And for the Vindication of that Cauſe and Party, which is dearer to me than my life, I ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to diſprove it, by reporting Naturally, the whole Series of their Behaviour, and deriving the Pedigree of Affairs, ſince the War.</p>
            <p>It muſt be acknowledged, That, from the time, when the two great Factions began firſt Viſibly to ſever, Though a few, the moſt Noble and ingenious of them, were early convinced of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61392:3"/>in ſeeking to reform alawful Government, by an unlawfull War, And endeavoured worthily to attone their guilt; Others, obſerving the tendency of Affairs to infinite Violence and Perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, became more wary, or, (as they termed it,) Moderate; Yet the Actions of that Party, for the mayn, declared, that they were ſtill fierce with Victory, and without Remorſe; True it is, that finding, by degrees their own Impotency to quell the ſpirits which they had raiſed or govern the Mutiny of their Souldiers, without an Eſtabliſhment; And withal ſuppoſing, that the King, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Cuſtody, would not, at his Peril, reject their Propoſitions, how hard of digeſtion ſoever they were; They ſent him Conditions to ſign, but not to conſider, much leſſe debate; Nor was it long, that they continued in this friendly Mood, But being eaſily ſcared by the Army, deſiſted from their Treaties; And, ſome Months after, the Vote of Non-Addreſſes paſſed both Houſes, in full Carreer, which, what pretence or gloſſe ſoever may be given it, (ſure I am,) It pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Petemptory Summons before Sentence, and an apt Prologue to our ſucceeding Tragedy, For, the King being once caſt off, the Captive was, afterwards, eaſily diſpoſed of.</p>
            <p>In the year 1648. the great Impoſture being, by this time, clearly unmasked, many others, who, at firſt, no queſtion, meant ſincerely, peceiving the total miſcarriage of their unadviſed Zeal, withdrew themſelves from their Faction, and frankly ſided with the Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts; Who, by this Acceſſion of Intereſts, and other probable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements, were encouraged, (though with diſadvantage e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) once more to Arme, for the prevention of ſo great and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Miſchiefs; Suddenly the whole Kingdom was full of Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections upon this Account, ſeconded with a powerful Invaſion from <hi>Scotland;</hi> And now, or never, (I take it,) was the Critical hour, for our Pretenders, to have expreſſed their Loyalty; Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then gaſping, and the ſacred head being viſibly expoſed; But, (contrarywiſe,) we felt their hands, in many places, heavier upon us, than the <hi>Independents,</hi> And, in Committees, eſpecially, they acted with all the violence imaginable.</p>
            <p>The Scotiſh Army being defeated, and the Royaliſts, every where, ſuppreſſed, the beſt Iſſue, that any good Engliſhman could now preſage, was very fatal; For though the Factions might ſeem to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, much like thoſe on <hi>Shooters-hill,</hi> ſome of them inclining only to bind the Traveller, and leave him helpleſſe in the adjacent Woods, Others, for their greater ſecurity from purſuit, determining
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61392:3"/>rather to kill him outright, Yet they agreed in the main deſign, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Robbery; The milder ſort of them, indeed, calmly diſſented from the Murther, profeſſing to abhor the needle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe effuſion of Royal Blood. But, whilſt the oppoſed only came Negotiations, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Actions, (as it commonly happens in Counſel, ſo managed,) Fury took Place. And, without interruption, finiſhed that accurſed Parricide.</p>
            <p>The Presbyterians ſeemed generally to be ſurpriſed, and even Planetſtruck, with this deadly blow, Nor could they, patiently, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Scandal of being accounted Privy, much leſſe Parties to the Action, or Contrivance; As if, (forſooth) they wondred to ſee him ſlain by others, whom, themſelves had ſorely threatned, and, in effect, out-lawed; Yet, had the Tragedy proved only perſonal, or had ſweet Ariſtocraſie next ſucceeded, together with Parochial Epiſcopacy, it is poſſible, the Pill might have been ſwallowed: But the Independent Party, having projected other deſigns, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to go through-ſtitch with their work, by the old Principle of Root and Branch, laboured, together, with Monarchy, to reform, <hi>(viz.)</hi> extirpate Peerage, Scattering withal, or rather ſowing, the popular ſeeds of toleration, which made the Breach, in appearance, irreparable; However, (after a breathing ſpace, civilly allowed them,) the tumour, of it ſelf, began to aſſwage; For many of the diſſenting Brethren, judging it, I ſuppoſe, unſeemly for them to continue long in a ſtate of diſcord, and profeſſing, that they would not ſtand upon Punctilios, where the publick was concerned, were, in a ſhort time reconciled to their enchanted Seats; Wherein the great Bug-bear of the times, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Common Enemy, was of ſingular advantage to them both: Wherefore, that all pretences might be duely acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated, and a certain Decorum in Affairs preſerved, (as it were by implicite Contract or Conſent) whilſt the Military Charge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained with Independents, as the ſurer Cards, the Civil Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with all its preheminencies reſted ſtill with Presbyterians, as the ſoberer Party, who had, likewiſe, a Major Vote in the Junto.</p>
            <p>Matters of Civil Policy being thus compounded, one would mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, that the Spiritual ſhould break any ſquares, or that either Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould be much troubled with a caſe of Conſcience; But as the Puloits had all along ſerved other ends, than that of Religion, ſo, now, it ſhould ſeem, the Clergy of thoſe times, (pardon me if I miſtake their quality,) finding themſelves utterly diſappointed of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61392:4"/>that Dominion, which they firſt aſpired to, and fearing yet a further downfal, by the daily growth of Independency, in deſpair of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their wiſhes by that Junto, which was awed by an Army, not of their Complexion, ſtirred up in the People, (eſpecially their own Diſciples,) a new diſaffection to their Rulers; Wherein, being animated from <hi>Scotland,</hi> they boldly Preached up the Covenant, which they had kept in Lavender for this or the like Occaſion; And, ſince they thought fit to remember their Covenant, they could not fairly forget their King, who (amongſt other matters of deeper deſign) was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herein mentioned, (as it were, of Courſe,) with reference to the times, for which it was firſt calculated: Wherefore, on a ſudden the Presbyterians grew very troubleſome, And ſomething they offered at, upon theſe Accounts, But with what kindneſſe to his Majeſty, I leave to any mans Judgement, For their Jealouſie of the Royal Intereſt increaſing, (eſpecially after their diſaſter at <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar,</hi>) inſtantly, they rather recoyled, than retreated, And, with their Numbers, Oppreſſed the King at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> chuſing rather to run their Riſquo with the Sectaries, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey hated, than take their Fortune with his Majeſty, whom they feared.</p>
            <p>Immediately upon this Miſcarriage, <hi>Scotland</hi> being ſubdued by the Forces of the Independents, The Intereſt of that Faction grew ſo prevalent, And their pretences ſo exorbitant, As involved all Perſons, of what Judgement ſoever, if either they had Eſtates, Profeſſions, or common foreſight, in an equal concernment to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch encroaching Anarchy, And, thereby, afforded <hi>Cromwell</hi> both a ſtirrop of great Advantage, and a convenient cloak for his Uſurpation, The People being Weather beaten, and willing to Anchor any where for preſent ſhelter; But ſtill it was with this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table difference, That, whilſt all good Engliſhmen looked upon themſelves as caſt upon a remote and barbarous Iſland, where they could not, or would not dwell; The Presbyterians, for the Major Part, judging, it ſeems, that they were at home, ſet up their Reſts and pitched their Tents there: And though all things did not fully anſwer their humours (which are hard to pleaſe,) Yet, having lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to permit ſomewhat to neceſſity, and ſhare what they could not engroſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e they found, (or rather made,) their condition very comfortable, Many of them, who had the faculty of ſhifting, and varying their forms, (as Sects and Inſects are, alike, apt to do,) kept ſteady footing in the Government, For, if the times did not comply with them, they, (to be ſure,) would comply with the times;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61392:4"/>Such, (being, no doubt, the choiceſt factours of Tyranny,) were the Uſurpers own Creatures, and poſſeſſed the chief Dignities &amp; Offices of State: All that had been once Roundheads, and would but hold their tongues, were countenanced in their ſeveral Wayes, And, if they could ſwallow a Gudgeon, ſure of great Preſerments, as they fell, However juſtified in all their illegal Poſſeſſions; The <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> with their odd Addreſſes, and Doctrines, magnifying ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Piety and Juſtice, ſometimes the Policy and Proweſſe of their Benefactour, were, by him, reciprocally entertained, as good Muſſulmen, with due encouragement, And to humour them throughout, their Pulpit Phraſes, Geſtures, and Tones, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly imitated and grew in faſhion at the Court: Thoſe, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be clogged with Principles, and could not walk up to the perfection of others, (being not very Numerous,) paſſed under the favourable Notion of tender Conſciences, or weak Brethren, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt whom, and the Uſurper, there was alwayes this General un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of each other, He, in his part, deſired to ſhew them, He took them not for Royaliſts, they, on their part, to ſatisfie him, That he had no reaſon to diſtruſt them: In ſum, The many Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies, which that Party did him in the <hi>Junto</hi> 1657. with teſtifie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record, That they were not utterly at defiance with him: On the other ſide, the Royaliſts, (unſhaken in their Fidelity, and unpolluted with the General Corruption, whether by Confederacy, Conſent, or Compliance,) reaſonably enough ſuppoſing, That, the Popular Baſis once undermined, ſuch Paper-buidings could not long continue, took heart again, And, (being withal enſnared, by the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pentine Practices of ſome Profeſſours,) freely embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued themſelves in great and hazardous deſigns to bring in the King; Which, being rather nipped, than ſuppreſſed, were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently reſumed, Every Year the Common Gaols were filled with Cavaliers, whereof, ſuch as the Tyrant could convict by the Juſtice of thoſe times, were, accordingly, diſpatched, ſuch as he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently ſuſpected, were ſent to Plantations, and remote Priſons, ſuch, as were only in his general Liſt, after ſome months durance, went out upon Bail, till the next Summons, or Warrant to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them, And this, I take it, may ſerve, at leaſt, for a Landship of that ſtrangely blended, and Promiſcuous Scene.</p>
            <p>After the Deceaſe of <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> It cannot be forgotten, with what reluctancy, the Souldiers and Phanaticks were brought to acknowledge his Son <hi>Richard,</hi> whom, ſoon after, they contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61392:5"/>diſcarded: The Souldiers Objected, That they had never known him in Arms, And that he was a Stranger to their Cauſe and Merit; The Fanaticks found him not for their turn, And were not willing to hazard their Affairs with him, in whoſe Experience or Conduct, they could no way confide; But the Presbyterians judging him to be naturally of their Principle, However, of ſoft Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and altogether dependant on their Intereſt, (as if their Sure were now Trump again) made him their Prince, And inclined, certainly, to have laid themſelves and their Country at his Feet, For the Pulpits, (the Oracles of Presbytery) recommended him to the People, as a man after Gods own heart.</p>
            <p>With the Fortune of <hi>Richard,</hi> fell all the hopes of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, For, in <hi>Junto's</hi> it was eaſily perceived, they would be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermatched by thoſe of the other faction, who were backed by the Army, and furniſhed with better Notions, as to the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, than they; And, from a free State, (if ſuch a Chymaera could then be fancied,) their Proſpect was yet more unpleaſant. Their Empire being, on all ſides, rejected, as the leaſt tolerable of any, that had been propounded; So as now they were put to find out a new Bottom, or rather an Expedient to preſerve themſelves, if not as Presbyterians, yet as men.</p>
            <p>Hitherto, I ſuppoſe their Modeſty will not pretend much of Loyalty; For making uſe only of their ambidextrous Covenant, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by adhering to the Letter, ſometimes by purſuing (as they ſaid,) the main End, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Reformation, They hovered, like a Cloud, uncertain where it ſhould drop, and lurked, as it were, in Ambuſcade, (like the <hi>Germane</hi> Boors, near a Battel,) ready to pillage either Party, when a diſaſter befell them; But now, conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather the preſent State and Exigence of Affairs, than their own Principles, or former Practiſes, They found a neceſſty of engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or remaining at the diſcretion of the Victour; For, on the one fide, they ſaw a deſperate faction, ſupported by a great Army, which muſt be maintained with Rapine, ſo as none could, in reaſon hope to be Innocent, that was rich, nor ſafe from them, but by adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with them; Beſides, that Tythes, and Colledges, being, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſwallowed, as the firſt ſweet Morſel, gave a ſhrill Alarm, Eſpecially to their Miniſters, who, ſurely, were not ſilent, or ſloathful in communicating their fears; On the other ſide, they found the People violently inclined to the King, exaſperated with their Burthens, weary of Unſettlement, and fearful of extreme Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61392:5"/>The Royaliſts full of freſh hopes, and ready for ſome notable Effort; And the King, (to whoſe Juſtice they ſaw themſelves very obnoxious, in caſe they endeavoured to make no Attonement,) not like to be long deſtitute of reaſonable Aid, by the general diſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Souldiers in Foraign Parts; Wherefore, (not to ſit dry, as they ſay, betwixt two great Rivers, (they Choſe to eſpouſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, as the ſafer and nobler Intereſt, being grounded on an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Baſis, which they obſerv'd the other wanted; But how lamely they proceeded, Let the year 1659 declare; For, though they knew; what reaſonable expectations were from them who had boaſted ſo much, And who indeed could come more eaſily to a Rendezvous, than the Royaliſts to a Private meeting, Though, for their encouragement, the right hand of Fellowſhip was civilly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded them, Their Atchievements, alas, were very Abortive; And, if we may judge from our Enemies Intelligence, by which they proceed to apprehend ſuſpected Perſons, It will ſoon appear, where the Burthen lay.</p>
            <p>Indeed, though ſome particular Perſons of them Acted, at that time, very clearly and honourably, yet the greater Number were, (at beſt,) Luke-warm, many Subtle ones, forejudging, I preſume, the Event of a Free Parliament, (then contended for,) declined the Enterpriſe; The Rigid Presbyterians, openly, branded it with Malignancy, And divers of their moſt famous Miniſters, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> publiſhed an Addreſſe to the Junto then ſitting, with their names ſubſcribed, beſeeching them, that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedneſſe of a few might not prejudice the integrity of many, who ſtill ſoberly adhered to their firſt Principles of a Godly Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and Miniſtery; So as, admitting the Faction to be more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, then, I truſt, it is, Yet the Diſſentours being ſo many, And the tempers of the reſt ſo various, I ſuppoſe their Endeavours might appear, perhaps the more generous, but could not be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, in proportion with the Royaliſts, who ſo freely engaged.</p>
            <p>From the Ruines of this deſign (how diſmall ſoever they appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,) there ſprung an unforeſeen, but conſiderable, advantage to the Kings Affairs, For <hi>Lambert,</hi> having, thereby, gotten a new Riſe of Fortune and Reputation with the Army, And finding by late ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, how eaſy and cheap it was to Uſurp, eſpecially, where the Uſurpation could not be more unwarrantable, or intollerable, than the Authority it ſelf, was incouraged to thruſt out that Junto, and ſet up a Committee of his own, with a purpoſe, no doubt, to follow
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61392:6"/>the very traces of <hi>Oliver;</hi> Wherein the whole fraternity, of Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, (Presbyterians excepted,) firmly adhered to him, as their great Captain, and Patron, who was to finiſh that work, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had left imperfect, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Subverſion of all our Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both in Church, and State; In order whereunto, the Confiding Party muſt be firſt refined, And the Notion of Malignancy ſpread as far, as Policy, or Avarice could extend it; In which danger ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly none were ſo near concerned as the New-Cavaliers (they being a freſh booty) but eſpecially the famous City of <hi>London,</hi> whoſe ſack, it was viſible, the Souldiers gaped for, And their Maſters were not very unlike to gratifie them therewith: Wherefore, if they would not altogether renounce their Senſes, They were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (as their laſt refuge) wholy to mingle Counſels with the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Party, and unite themſelves to that Cauſe, which was then very Popular, And could only in appearance give check to ſo foul and fierce a Monſter, Or reſcue them from Captivity, under thoſe, that meaſure the Rights of others by their own Luſts.</p>
            <p>In this Confuſion of Intereſts, enervating and ſupplanting each other, His Grace, the Duke of <hi>Albemarle,</hi> (who, with profound Secrecy, had, till then, reſerved himſelf for ſuch a Juncture,) wiſely judged, That Now was his only Opportunity of Acting, For in diſſipating the Fanaticks, by the Colliſion of Parties, He ſhould Cut the Sinews of Faction, and advance proſperouſly, upon their Bellies, towards freedome, and lawful ſettlement; And, though to vanquiſh an Army, ſo reſolved, and appointed, with ſlender Troops, on which he could little rely, ſeemed almoſt impoſſible, Yet, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying his want of Forces, by his Conduct, and correcting their ſtubborneſſe with Excellent Diſcipline, with great aſſurance, he committed the Event to Providence; The Authority he made uſe of, was that of the late Junto, which, (how frivolous ſoever in it ſelf,) was the beſt then in being, And, indeed, afforded him ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient colour againſt his Enemy, who acted mutinouſly under that Commiſſion, From thence, therefore he determined to take his Riſe, by the Example of good Builders, who, to erect a lofty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, lay the Foundation low, Foreſeeing, no doubt, That as <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> and his Confederates were very Guilty to the Powers, by them interrupted; Thoſe Powers were no leſſe obnoxious to the Excluded Members, And they again to an entire Parliament; So that publick intereſt, being one in motion, probably would never reſt, till, by continual progreſſe it came to center in our Antient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61392:6"/>and Natural Conſtitutions. His Succeſſe was ſuitable to the Merit of his deſign; For, by Civil Stratagems, added to his Military Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, Temporiſing, and Amuſing his Enemy with uncertain Treaties, he ſoon diſſolved that Veterane Army, without hazarding ſo much as a Skirmiſh.</p>
            <p>This, indeed, was a fair and Auſpicious Introduction to better things, But, alas, Our deliverance was as yet, a meer Embrio, And, (if here forſaken,) Subject to fatal miſcarriage; Whereof his Grace being very ſenſible, he reſolved to perfect it, by comming with his Victorious Army to <hi>London:</hi> His Pretence was very favourable, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The final Suppreſſion of the Fanaticks, who otherwiſe might eaſily be encouraged to make head again, Wherefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt taking, and asking leave, preventing reſiſtance, or denyal, with a Sober and Orderly Expedition, he advanced Southward, But, in his March, received Addreſſes of all kinds, with ſuch Indifferent Behaviour, and Anſwers ſo like Oracles, as, at once, gave Courage to his Friends, yet Hope to his Enemies, and brought him, undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, to his Journeys End; Where acting, Yet, for a time, the ſame Perſon, having, by an unheard of Stratagem, throughly felt the Pulſes of the People, and caught the Malicious in their own Net; He ſeaſonably appeared, what he alwayes was, A Perfect Lover of his Country.</p>
            <p>In the Glory of which enterpriſe, (the moſt fortunate and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable of our times,) Let not any Party or Faction pretend to ſhare; It being freſh in our Memories, That neither Presbyterians, nor Royaliſts were ſo Convinced, or Satisfied of his Graces Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (the Diſguiſal whereof was then his Maſterpiece,) that they thought it fit, or ſafe for them, to engage with him, But the whole Nation ſtood muſing, in a kind of Trance, full of various thoughts, and diſcourſes concerning him, Inclining, doubtleſſe to wiſh him well, Yet rather deſirous, to know why.</p>
            <p>The Welcome of this Notable Deliverance both from preſent and future Violences, was Celebrated with unuſual Triumphs: For, as well the People in general, as the Royal Party, being therewith ſurpriſed, could ſcarce contain themſelves, but were tranſported with Exceſſe of Joy, Wherein the Presbyterians ſeemed alſo to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take; But (like Perſons, who debauching over night, are Crop-ſick the next morning,) No ſooner was the publick ſecurity digeſted, but they began immediately to conſult the concernments of their Faction, And examine, Whether the Liberty, long deſired, and then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61392:7"/>expected by the People, would not blaſt, and finally fruſtrate their hopes, which were inconſiſtent with ſuch Liberty; Many of their Countenances betrayed a kind of Chagrin, or ſecret regret, which, for ſhame, they muſt not own, And accordingly, from henceforth, their Buſineſſe was, not ſo much to bring in his Majeſty, (which no Endeavours of theirs could greatly expedite, or obſtruct,) As to contrive and limit the Manner of his Entrance, that it might ſerve their purpoſes: His Grace, (no queſtion,) knew a Part of their minds, And, to make his Paſſage, as clear as might be, reſolved to gratifie them, in all things conſiſtent with his deſign; Wherefore, purſuing his Method of effecting that, ſecurely, by degrees, which could not, (without manifeſt hazard,) be, at once, accompliſhed, Inſtead of a new and free Election, (the Popular pretence,) He per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Members, excluded in 1648. to take their places, and Act as a Houſe of Commons, without the Lords, But, firſt agreed with them of a time of Seſſion ſo ſhort, as might afford them no latitude to conſider ought, but what was in Order to their own diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and the Summons of a freer Convention, Keeping that other Expedient, as a reſerve, in Caſe they ſhould herein prevaricate with him.</p>
            <p>The Excluded Members were, generally, Perſons, who, by long Experience, had acquired much Prudence, and Moderation; And great Matters were in reaſon expected from them, whom it highly concerned, at length, to perform their Vowes, and redeem their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; Yet, (Whether they only yielded to the Iniquity of the times, (as many alleadged,) Or (as others doubted,) their teeth were ſtill on Edge with the ſower Grapes, they had once eaten,) Certain it is, That the Subſcription by them impoſed in the Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Militia, And their narrow Confinement of Elections be excluding even the Sons of Royaliſts, afforded matter of much Scandal, and evil Prognoſtick, That they only wanted Elbow-room for further Severity; Neither, indeed, was their unwillingneſſe to quit their beloved Seats, without ſpecial Notice; But they ſoon made amends for all, by their much deſired diſſolution, Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Interval of Government to a Select Counſel of Eſtate.</p>
            <p>During which Interval, the great Argument of our Cabales was this, <hi>viz.</hi> What would be the force of thoſe Shackles, wherewith both Parliament and Militia were then charged; There being ſcarce ever the like Engines of Faction, invented, by the late Refiners; ſo as moſt of thoſe, whoſe Complexions were not ſanguine, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaged
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61392:7"/>that all the ſatisfaction we had ſwallowed, muſt be vomited up again: His Grace was generally acquitted, as having done his part, for it could not be expected, that he ſhould inſpire Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it was for him ſufficient, that reſcuing them from outward interruptions, he both enabled, and directed them to do good: But, whilſt matters thus continued in great ſuſpenſe, it pleaſed God to ſend a ſtrong Eaſt wind, with a Spring-tide of Loyalty, which overwhelmed all thoſe Banks and Damms, wherein the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititians thought themſelves ſo ſecure: For the Royaliſts, rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending, that then was the very Criſis of their future hopes, ſome of them generouſly deſpiſing thoſe Qualifications, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great Penalties diſabled them, others, moſt induſtriouſly aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Elections; The People perceiving and declining the ſnare; and his Grace continually favouring the Cauſe of Freedom, as the only Groundwork of his Proceeding, the Major Vote of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, (by Gods Bleſſing,) proved ſuch, as hath produced the Peace and happineſſe we now enjoy.</p>
            <p>Had his Majeſty lain at the Presbyterians feet, it is probable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, they would, at length, have brought him in, if not out of Loyalty, yet for quietneſſe ſake, ſince, without him, they found, there could be no Settlement; But, then, he muſt have taken Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions from them, and ſuch, as would have rendred, it doubtful, whether a Diadem, ſo qualified and Circumſcribed, were worth his acceptance; The Church muſt have been relinquiſhed, and all the Sacriledge of the times eſtabliſhed, with his conſent; His Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty forſaken, and condemned as Felons; Laws ſhould have been made, and executed only in his name: Upon theſe, and other the like Agreements, he might, perhaps, have obtained an honourable Penſion, together with a Writ of eaſe; That whilſt he Reigned, they might Rule, as a kind of Ephori; So that, at beſt, they may be ſaid to have contributed to the bringing in of a King of <hi>Sparta,</hi> but not of an Engliſh Monarch; In a word, either they renounced, or retained their Principles; If they retained them, they could not with any reaſon, be preſumed to act, with ſo little Conformity to themſelves, and their Affairs, if they renounced, they were, then, no longer Presbyterians.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if we examine the demeanour of many ſince our bleſſed Change, we ſhall have little ground to believe, that they were great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſollicitous for the bringing in of his Majeſty, whom, (pardoning with abundant clemency, and governing (as he doth) with infinite
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61392:8"/>Moderation,) they can yet leſſe afford to comply with, than they could with the worſt of Tyrants; But by their continual ſnarling, their readineſſe to report and improve Calumnies, their delight in any thing, that may ſeem to croſſe his Majeſties wiſhes, their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbial Interlocutions, importing Menaces, and Deſigns Above all, their flocking to ſeditious Preachers and Lecturers, declare that we owe our Settlement, rather to their weakneſſe, than their Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Alas, it is for men of noble and ſincere minds, to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by reaſon, or reclaimed by benefits, Levened Natures are not ſoon purged, nor Cities, overgrown with Faction, eaſily weeded: And ſince, under long Perſecutions, the Royal Party not only kept their own ſtation, but, ſelling their Inheritances, entailed their Principles, to their Familes Why ſhould any imagine, that our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours are regenerate, ſince the Kings return: I wiſh his Majeſties goodneſſe to them, find a due requital, and this Argument prove a falſe Alarm, which, at all Events, is ſafer, perhaps, than none.</p>
            <p>Some, I hear, have undertaken to draw a kind of parallel, betwixt our principal Covenanters, and the Lords of the League in <hi>France,</hi> concerning their return to their obedience; But, I ſuppoſe, the diſparity will appear to be vaſt and important: Thoſe in <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſſeſſed of ſtrong Garriſons, and entire Provinces at their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, had it in their choice, whether they would preſent them, as Peace-offerings to their Prince, or make uſe of their Advantages, (as ſome did) to diſ-member the Kingdom. It was otherwiſe here, for, his Grace having once muzzled the Army, and thereby freed the Nation from its bondage, there remained nothing, that could obſtruct our immediate Settlement, or afford leiſure for any to capitulate with his Majeſty; Again, the holy League was not infringed by any notorious prevarication that might blaſt its Credit, But the Covenant, being trampled on by the Impoſers, was grown as vile as Dung, as ſcandalous, as the ſtewes, and had done all the Miſchief it could: Finally, the Leaguers had never, perſonally, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliged the King, nor affronted the Crown; And, ſince their Quarrel was purely Religious, (though ſurely, therein extravagant enough, yet) after that Kings converſion to the Romane Faith, whereby, he partly purged them of their guilt and ſcandal, there was little fear of their Loyalty, for the time to come; Whereas, our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, having greatly injured their Soveraign, and being poiſoned in their Principles, as to the Government, may, probably, ſtill continue as Thornes in the ſide of Monarchy, and have therefore of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61392:8"/>late been juſtly branded with an indelible Character of reproach, So that, I preſume, the ſame Arguments cannot ſerve them both, either in relation to merit antecedent, or future confidence.</p>
            <p>Hitherto, I have chiefly argued their want of Inclination to ſerve his Majeſty, if further it ſhall appear, that they likewiſe, wanted power, I hope, it will then be readily granted, that the work was not theirs: Now, what, in reaſon, could be expected from thoſe, who by their manifold Perjuries, and Impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ures, (long ſince detected,) had forfeited all their Intereſt and Reputation with honeſt or ſober men; It was eaſie, indeed, at the firſt to do miſchief, to diſturb a lawful and peaceable Government, For, in combuſtible matter, even little ſparkes, (unquenched,) have kindled great flames, and ſedition is commonly the work of mean Varlets: But, to prevent diſaſters, or redreſſe them, to encounter Tyrants, and reſtore lawful Powers, is no ſleight atchievement: Briefly, that Party, which in a free Election, could ſcarce be choſen to ſerve for any one County, nor, indeed pretend to it, but in a few, will not, I ſuppoſe, arrogate to it ſelf a national Intereſt, nor can it ſeem to be any way conſiderable, without faction, or uſurped Power.</p>
            <p>From all which, it is manifeſt, that, to God only belongs the glory of his Majeſties Preſervation, and our deliverance, To the blood of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, and other noble Aſſertours of his Cauſe, ſhed in its defence, the vertue and renown, by which it hath out-lived its ruine, To his Grace, the Duke of <hi>Albermarle,</hi> (next under God,) the honour of redeeming his Country, and reſtoring his Soveraign, without bloodſhed, or ſervile Conditions; To the Royal Party, this juſt Commendation, that by their reſtleſs endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and matchleſs conſtancy, they harraſſed all the Sentinels of Tyranny, with duty and fatigue, blunted the edge of Perſecution, and ſeaſoning the people continually, both with wholeſome Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and great examples, (like the Salt of their Country,) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it from putrefaction, in the worſt of times; To the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, this ſingle Character, that they acted all along like prudent men, who knew a better uſe to be made of Conſcience than by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for it, and that having tryed all expedients of Settlement, or ſecurity, without the King, and found them ineffectual, they at length, inclined to the bringing in of his Majeſty, leſt he ſhould have come in without them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
